Okay great. Today's דף daf is דף ל"ו. Daf Lamed Vav. No,
דף ל"ז. Daf Lamed Zayin. Okay. But we're going to start on
ל"ו Lamed Vav on the משנה Mishnah at the bottom of the
משנה Mishnah right there. Okay? So take a look.
סנהדרין היתה כחצי גורן עגולה כדי שיהיו רואין זה את זה. Sanhedrin
hayetah kechatzi goren agulah kedei sheyihiyu roin zeh et zeh.
So we're talking about the shape of the סנהדרין. Sanhedrin. The סנהדרין
Sanhedrin itself was set up such so that it was like half
of a threshing floor that was shaped in a half circle so
that everyone could see one another. Okay so this is my beautiful
picture I put on the board right now. This is the סנהדרין.
Sanhedrin. These are say the people who are actually coming in and
this as we're going to see soon are going to be three
rows of תלמידי חכמים Talmidei Chachamim scholars who are going to be
sitting there waiting and possibly entering the, becoming judges of the סנהדרין
Sanhedrin themselves. Okay. ושני סופרי הדיינים עומדים לפניהם אחד מימין ואחד משמאל
Ushenei sofrei hadayanin omdim lifneihem echad miyamin ve'echad mismol and there's two
court scribes that are there too on the sides, one on the
right hand side and one on the left hand side. וכותבין דברי
מחייבין ודברי מזכין Vekotvin divrei mechaivin vedivrei mezakin and they write the
words of the accused, right, the guilty party here, it's interesting, the
accused and that of the the one who is innocent. רבי יהודה
אומר שלשה. Rabbi Yehuda omer sheloshah. No, actually there were three court
scribes. אחד כותב דברי המזכין ואחד כותב דברי המחייבין והשלישי כותב דברי
המזכין ודברי המחייבין. Echad kotev divrei hamezakin ve'echad kotev divrei hamechaivin vehashelishi
kotev divrei hamezakin vedivrei hamechaivin. So there's actually one person who's completely
in charge of the accuser, one person who's completely in charge of
writing the words of the defendant, and a third one who writes
both. רש"י Rashi I think says that's in order to make sure
there's no mistakes that are actually made. He's like the checker. Or
at least soon afterwards.
And each one writes both.
Each one writes both. Ah, so רש"י Rashi also says that because
it's too much work. It's like they would worry about them coming
into mistakes because they'd be so busy. So in this way you're
sure one person gets one person, one person gets the other person,
and there's a check built in. Okay, great.
Where do these scribes stand?
Where do these scribes stand? I think I don't know, it's not
entirely clear. It says one from the left and one from the
right. So I'm not sure, okay? Great.
But it's not to the right of the litigant.
I don't think so, but I can't promise. Okay, let's keep on
going. ושלש שורות של תלמידי חכמים יושבין לפניהם כל אחד ואחד מכיר
את מקומו. Veshalosh shurot shel talmidei chachamim yoshvin lifneihem kol echad ve'echad
makir et mekomo.
Okay,
so now we get to these three lines of תלמידי חכמים Talmidei
Chachamim that are sitting there in wait. We'll see what for.
הוצרכו לסמוך סומכין מן הראשונה אחד מן השניה בא לו לראשונה אחד
מן השלישית בא לו לשניה.
Hutzrechu
lismoch
somchin min harishonah echad min hasheniyah ba lo larishonah echad min hashelishit
ba lo lasheniyah. And tell me how many. I will, don't worry.
At least רש"י Rashi will tell us. Each individual knows their place.
If they need to appoint a judge then they appoint one from
the first row.
רש"י Rashi explains that there's actually... actually I'm going to take
this so I...
Great,
amazing.
Now you're up. Now you're up. You can plug it
back in.
Sorry about that.
Okay, if it doesn't work that's fine, people can watch online. Okay.
So if you look at the first רש"י Rashi on the top
where it says ושלש שורות כל אחד כמנין סנהדרי עשרים ושלשה Veshalosh
shurot kol echad keminyan Sanhedri esrim usheloshah each one of these rows
is as, in the same number that's on the סנהדרין Sanhedrin itself.
We're talking about the small סנהדרין Sanhedrin here, not the large one,
so there's twenty-three judges in the סנהדרין. Sanhedrin. Okay, that's our case.
Our case is the court of twenty-three. שאם יחלקו הכנסת הגדולה רובן
מחייבין ומיעוט מזכין והטייה לרעה אין על פי אחד She'im yechalku hakenesset
hagedolah ruban mechaivin umi'ut mezakin vehatayah lera'ah ein al pi echad right?
So
when we're talking about a capital case, that's why we're in the
סנהדרין. Sanhedrin. Not
necessarily. But the case we're talking about, the example, you're right, the
example he's giving right now is that of a capital case because
he's explaining why would you need a situation where you would have
to add in judges from these rows? Okay? So the situation he's
giving is as we know in a capital case you can't have
a verdict given out where there is... Wait. 35 to 36. Now
you can't add any more judges. 71 is the maximum. So now
we're stuck. Now we're stuck. So now what do we do? We
have to release him. Right. You release the defendant. We're going to
use the word פוטרין. potrin. To release is to פוטר poter him.
One more judge that says you're guilty than says you're innocent. You
need at least two in order for the case to be carried
out. So he's saying okay what happens if you have 21 versus
no sorry what's 32 my addition is not
good 36 and 30 36 and 35 no no no we're talking
about the 32 okay so I don't know whatever the math is
I can't promise I don't know what the math is at the
moment but you have one more person says you're guilty so in
that case you add two more judges from the first row okay
amazing 32 or 23 you say oh sorry 23 that's
what I'm saying
there we go okay so there we go so it's 12 and
11 there we go you solved the problem okay it's 12 judges
and 11 judges okay so 12 say you're guilty and 11 say
you're innocent then you need to and they can't come to any
sort of conclusion then you bring two more judges
from right here right this is these are the best guys sitting
here and it goes slightly less better on the first row and
then you get the second row okay and there's 23 here 23
here and 23
here
okay great so remember what he's saying though we're going to we're
going to keep on going okay because we don't have that much
time והוזקקנו להושיב בפניהם ארבעים ושמונה Vehizkaknu lehoshiv bifneihem arbaim ushmonah
okay
so he's going to say actually right you should have to
get 48 more judges here because the maximum number of judges you
can have in the סנהדרין Sanhedrin once you add in all the
judges is up to 71 there can be no court that has
more than 71 judges okay and so he's saying oh okay so
you need 48 right if my math is correct which yeah in
this case it actually happens to be you need 48 plus 23
equals right right so hold on it's actually 48 this one I'm
sure about it's 48 plus the 23 that are here okay however
as we see there actually aren't 48 here right and so רש״י
Rashi needs to explain why that is
so he's saying oh whatever I'm not going to go through all
of it inside basically you can look in inside but basically he's
saying there should be the same amount of
you shouldn't have more than 23 in each row that's why we
have multiple rows because then it would be like a disrespect to
the judges that are actually sitting here
and okay if that's the case then why wouldn't you have 23
23 and then 2 right 23 23 plus 2 plus the original
23 equals 71 over there in
the original
the
סנהדרין Sanhedrin no no no we're talking about the small סנהדרין Sanhedrin
okay we're talking about this is 23 now I'll write that down
we're not talking about a situation of 71 we're talking about a
situation of 23 okay I realize that
yes so they need any סנהדרין Sanhedrin even the one of 23
which
is דווקא davka 23 in this case okay
oh but not the great סנהדרין Sanhedrin
no we're not talking about that right now okay only 23 sorry
I think I should have been more clear here okay so if
you have 23 23 and then you would have 2 more here
to create the 71 so he says no it's not nice to
have 2 guys sitting in the back here right we want all
the rows to be equal okay let's keep on going back to
the גמרא Gemara
well there's there's 21 of those guys who know they'll never be
picked yeah they're just hanging out
yeah okay true it's a strange situation I don't know what to
tell you okay we're going back to the משנה Mishna okay right
והוצרכו לסמוך סומכים מן
הראשונה
vehotzrechu lismoch
somchim min harishonah
so if you need to add judges you just add judges from
the beginning בא לו לראשונה אחד מן השניה ba lo lerishonah echad
min hashniyah sorry סומכים מן הראשונה אחד מן השניה בא לו לראשונה
somchim min harishonah echad min hashniyah ba lo lerishonah
so someone from the second line
gets to go to the first line now
right one of the guys in the first line gets
pulled up exactly they get moved up and you get moved up
in line right it's like you're waiting at the what's it called
DMV exactly okay and so בא לו לראשונה אחד מן השניה ba
lo lerishonah echad min hashniyah oh אחד מן השלישית בא
לו לשניה echad min hashlishit ba lo lishniyah
okay same thing from the third to the second line ובוררין להם
עוד אחד מן הקהל uborerin lahem od echad min hakahal
okay so you need all of these rows not only that but
you need all of these rows actually filled so once this guy
from the third line goes up to the second line you take
someone from the audience the people who are watching and you stick
them in that third line
so even like a complete ignoramus
it doesn't say here I don't know what knowledge you need you're
never going to get to him it doesn't matter he's never going
to be a judge right but you need those lines filled okay
ומושיבין אותו
בשלישית
umoshivin
oto bashlishit
and you place him in the third line ולא היה יושב במקומו
של ראשון אלא יושב במקום הראוי לו velo hayah yoshev bimkomo shel
rishon ela yoshev bimkom haraui lo
okay so what does that mean that means you don't place him
in the spot that was left open
from the
let's say there was some situation where the spot was here rather
everyone moves up one line okay great so let's go to the
גמרא Gemara מנא הני מילי mna hani mili okay
and if you look at the רש״י Rashi
מנא הני מילי mna hani mili in the גמרא Gemara it says
דבאגולה היו יושבין debaagulah hayu yoshvin
so where do we derive that this this half circle Okay. אמר
רבי אחא, Amar Rabbi Akha, said רבי אחא בר חנינא, Rabbi Akha
bar Chanina, דאמר קרא, de-amar kra,
it comes from the verse שררך אגן הסהר אל יחסר המזג. Shorerech
aggan hasahar al yechsar hamazeg.
Your belly button is like
a crescent basin. There should not there is not lacking in mixing.
We're talking about wine, mixing wine. Okay, now we're going to go
through each of these different parts of this פסוק pasuk from שיר
השירים. Shir Hashirim. It's very interesting that we're taking a פסוק pasuk
from שיר השירים Shir Hashirim to talk about the סנהדרין, Sanhedrin, right?
Okay, שררך, Shorerech,
זו סנהדרין. zo Sanhedrin. למה נקרא שמה שררך? Lama nikra shema shorerech?
So your belly button, that's talking about the סנהדרין. Sanhedrin. Why is
it called your belly button? שהיא יושבת בטיבורו של עולם, she-hi yoshevet
be-tiburo shel olam, because the סנהדרין Sanhedrin sits in the navel of
the world. Okay, that's the the Temple. We're talking about these other
מדרשים midrashim that talk about the Temple being the the navel of
the world. אגן, Aggan, why do we say basin? שהיא מגינה, she-hi
megina, notice the wordplay, אגן Aggan because it protects על כל העולם
כולו, al kol ha-olam kulo, the entire world.
הסהר, Ha-sahar, crescent, and this is the part that's actually relevant for
us, שהיא דומה לסהר she-hi doma le-sahar because it's in the same
shape as a crescent.
Okay, where are we? דומה לסהר. doma le-sahar. אל יחסר המזג, Al
yechsar ha-mazeg, its mixing should not be lacking, right? Mixing. Back in
the day they used to mix wine and water. אם הוצרך אחד
מהם לצאת רואין אם יש עשרים ושלושה. im hutsrach echad mehem latzet
ro-in im yesh esrim u-shlosha.
If one of the judges needs to leave, you see if there
are twenty-three in the audience here, כנגד סנהדרי קטנה יוצא ואם לאו
אינו יוצא. keneged sanhedrei ketana yotze ve-im lav eino yotze.
So if there were twenty-three waiting, then he's allowed to leave if
he has important business to attend to. Okay.
There might be a time where there is there aren't three full
rows.
Yeah, it seems like this is the ideal and this is like
oh okay so in a בדיעבד bedi-avad situation where there aren't these
these rows. Right, right. And also we'll see there's also later on
there seems to be a crowd of people watching too this was
still like a spectacle.
Well they're going to come in and go anyway so there has
to be a crowd of people watching that's for sure.
Interesting I didn't know that.
Did you say שורש shoresh of אגן aggan basin and protection הגנה?
agana? Is it mentioned here?
Oh okay right right there's wordplay there there's wordplay there.
In the body.
Yeah that's because of the shape of the bone. Okay.
בטנך ערמת חטים, Bitnech aremat
chitim, מה ערמת חטים הכל נהנין ממנה אף סנהדרין הכל נהנין ממנה.
ma aremat chitim ha-kol nehenin mimena af sanhedrin ha-kol nehenin mimena.
Okay,
so now we're going to we're continuing in שיר השירים Shir Hashirim
where it says your stomach is like a a mound of wheat.
Okay, so why does this have to do with סנהדרין? Sanhedrin? מה
ערמת חטים, Ma aremat chitim,
just as a mound of wheat everyone, everyone likes a mound of
wheat right?
All benefit from wheat. אף סנהדרין הכל נהנין מטעמיהם, Af sanhedrin ha-kol
nehenin mi-ta'amehem,
everyone loves the reasons of the the סנהדרין Sanhedrin gives in the
פסק psak in their legal cases. Okay. So now we keep on
going even though it's a different subject nevertheless we're going to still
talk about שיר השירים. Shir Hashirim. סוגה בשושנים. Suga bashoshanim. Okay, a
hedge of roses.
שאפילו כסוגה של שושנים לא יפרצו בהן פרצות. she-afilu ke-suga shel shoshanim
lo yifretzu bahen pratzot.
So so even a hedge of roses or something that is as
thin or as easy to pass through as a hedge of roses,
they, we're talking about the Jewish people here, will not end up
breaking through it. היינו דאמר ליה ההוא מינא לרב כהנא. Hainu de-amar
le-hahu mina le-rav kahana. It's like this case where there was a
heretic who was talking to רב כהנא. Rav Kahana.
אמריתו נדה שרי לייחודי בהדי גברא. Amritu nida shari le-yichudi bahadei gavra.
So you say that a נדה nida is allowed to be in
ייחוד yichud with, we're talking about the husband here, with her husband?
אפשר אש בנעורת ואינה מהבהבת? Efshar esh be-no-oret ve-eina mehaphphet? Could it
be that there is a situation where there is fire amongst flax
and does not singe it? Right? Meaning like how could this be?
This is clear clearly they're going to come to transgress. אמר ליה
התורה העידה עלינו סוגה בשושנים שאפילו כסוגה בשושנים לא יפרצו בהן
פרצות. Amar leh ha-torah he-ida aleinu suga bashoshanim she-afilu ke-suga bashoshanim lo
yifretzu bahen pratzot. So the Torah told us that a hedge of
roses, right? From שיר השירים, Shir Hashirim, that a barrier
even as thin as a hedge of roses, the Jewish people will
not come to transgress the laws that have to do with this
subject. And תוספות Tosafot brings up an interesting point here, which I
won't go to inside, but nevertheless he's disturbed because תוספות Tosafot says
that
that ייחוד yichud is דאורייתא. de-oraita. So if ייחוד yichud is דאורייתא,
de-oraita, how could it be that we have some verse in שיר
השירים Shir Hashirim that is coming to override a דאורייתא de-oraita law?
And so he ends. understands that no, actually, the דאורייתא *DeOraisa* of
יחוד *Yichud* only applies to specific cases when the
relationship between the two people in question
one you're always forbidden to sleep, one is always forbidden to sleep
with the other, like you know close relatives or things like that,
but not in the case of husband and wife.
Okay, back to the גמרא Gemara, *Gemara*. ריש לקיש אמר מהכא *Resh
Lakish amar me'hacha*: כפלח הרמון רקתך *Ke'pelach harimon rakatech*. ריש לקיש *Resh
Lakish* says no, actually,
that now we're still talking about the fact that of יחוד *Yichud*,
okay? ריש לקיש
*Resh Lakish* says no, it actually comes from this verse: like a
wedge of pomegranate is your temple. אפילו ריקנים שבך מלאים מצוות כרמון
*Afilu rikanim shebach male'im mitzvot karimon*. Even those who are the most
like, literally means empty, but we're talking about like the lowest of
the low, even they are full of מצוות *mitzvos* like a pomegranate.
רבי זירא אמר מהכא *Rabbi Zeira amar me'hacha*: וירח את ריח בגדיו
*Vayarach es reiach begadav*. אל תקרי בגדיו אלא בוגדיו *Al tikrei begadav
ela bogdav*. So this is interesting, right? This comes from when יעקב
*Yaakov* is tricking his father יצחק *Yitzchak* into thinking that he is
his brother עשיו *Eisav*. And he smells, his the father יצחק *Yitzchak*
smells the clothes, which smell like עשיו *Eisav*. And here it says,
and he smelled the smell of his clothes. Don't read clothes, rather
his
traitors. Thank you. Right, rather his traitors, which is kind of amazing.
Usually the מדרשים *midrashim* here try to justify יעקב
*Yaakov*'s actions, and here we say that we call him a בוגדיו
*bogdav*, a traitor, or someone who—it's not really a traitor here, I
don't think they mean—I think they mean like someone who misleads. But
the idea is nevertheless he's smelling his clothes, so it must be
a beautiful smell, the fact that he's smelling it means that even
in a situation where they're traitors or misleaders, nevertheless they have a
beautiful smell. What's that have to do with יחוד *Yichud*?
Because we
trust even the lowest of the low, right? I mean not to
call whatever יעקב *Yaakov* the lowest of the low, but even those
who are being
dishonest, nevertheless they have a good smell, right? They won't transgress this.
This is what the תורה *Torah* said, you know, he smelled his
clothes and it smelled like the fragrance of the field. Oh, thank
you.
It's explicit. Thank you.
That he liked very much, you know.
Great, so the תורה *Torah* is, thank you, explicitly says it's a
good smell, not just a smell. So that's helpful.
Okay.
Okay, so now we're going to go on to a similar situation.
הנהו בריוני דהוו בשיבבותיה דרבי זירא *Hanu biryonei de-hava be-shivuvusei de-Rabbi Zeira*.
So there were some thugs in the neighborhood of רבי זירא *Rabbi
Zeira*. דהוה מקרב להו *De-hava mekarev lehu*, and he would hang out
with them. כי היכי דניהדרו להו בתשובה *Ki heichi de-nehadru lehu bi-teshuvah*,
so that they would do תשובה *teshuvah*, do repentance. והוו קפדי רבנן
*Ve-hava kapdi Rabbanan*, and the רבנן *Rabbanan* were very angry about this
fact that רבי זירא *Rabbi Zeira* would hang out with them. כי
נח נפשיה דרבי זירא *Ki nach nafshei de-Rabbi Zeira*, and when רבי
זירא *Rabbi Zeira* died, אמרי עד האידנא הוה חריכא קטין שקי דהוה
בעי עלן רחמי השתא מאן בעי עלן רחמי *amri ad ha-idana hava
haricha ketin shakei de-hava ba'ei alan rachamei Hashta man ba'ei alan rachamei*.
So when he died, these thugs would say, now that singed
small legs—that's what they would call רבי זירא *Rabbi Zeira*, was singed
small legs. רש"י Rashi *Rashi*, I think, I don't remember, there's
a whole story that he like sat in the oven or...
Yeah, exactly.
Thank you. So that's what רש"י Rashi *Rashi* mentions that, that it
comes from בבא מציעא *Bava Metzia*. So there's, he was רבי זירא
*Rabbi Zeira* was someone who was a very pious man who would
like fast a lot and afflict himself. So one of his afflictions
maybe were like putting his legs in heat or something like that,
and so he ended up. And also he was known as someone
who is very short and squat kind of and didn't have a
necessarily pleasing appearance. So anyway, both these thugs and other people would
call him singed small legs. He would pray for us, but now
who's going to pray for us? Then הרהרו בלבייהו ועבדו תשובה *hirhiru
belibehu ve-avdu teshuvah*. So they searched their hearts and did תשובה *teshuvah*.
Okay, nice.
What, sorry, how does this connect? I mean even they did תשובה
*teshuvah*, correct, maybe they
could be trusted.
Correct, I think we're just on the theme of the lowest of
the low
of
Jews actually being higher than you think. I think that's the connection
I think. Okay. Cool. Okay, שלש שורות *shalosh shurot*. So now we're
going back to these three lines of תלמידי חכמים *talmidei chachamim* that
of scholars that are sitting there. אמר אביי Abaye, *Amar Abaye*. So
אביי *Abaye* said, שמע מינה *shma mina*. When one of these individuals
in this
and these rows moves forward, all of
them move forward.
There doesn't become an empty space here. Okay. ולימא להו עד האידנא
הוה יתיבנא ברישא השתא מותיביתו לי בזנבי? So imagine if there's someone
sitting here, they're in the best place in the second line, right?
They're sitting in number one spot. This goes from number one down
to twenty-three. And so now we're moving up, everyone's moving up one
space, and he's going from best place in the second row to
the worst space in number two, right? That seemingly, I guess for
this guy, wouldn't be any good. So he says, until this point
I've been at the head, and now you're placing me in the
tail? אמר אביי דאמרי לה הכי. Amar Abaye d'amrei lah hachi. Says
אביי, that's like they say, הוי זנב לאריות ואל תהי ראש לשועלים.
Havei zanav l'arayot v'al tehi rosh l'shualim. You might have heard this
phrase before. It's right, you should be a tail for a lion
and not a head for a fox. Okay. So better to be
the worst in amongst a good group of people than the best
of a group of not so good people. Okay. Now let's move
on to the משנה. mishnah. What are we doing on time? Oh,
I need to speed up a little bit. Okay. כיצד מאיימין את
העדים? Keitzad me'aymin et ha'edim? So how do you threaten the עדים
edim literally? As we see, we're going to be warning them about
the importance of human life. Okay. These are going to be עדים
edim in a capital trial of a capital case that one would
be judged in a court of twenty-three. Okay. על עידי נפשות היו
מכניסין אותן ומאיימין עליהם. Al edei nefashot hayu machnisin otan u'me'aymin aleihem.
When we're talking about witnesses in capital cases, they would bring them
into this area of the סנהדרין Sanhedrin and they would threaten them.
שמא תאמרו מאומד ומשמועה מפי עד ועד מפי עד ופי אדם נאמן.
Shema tomaru me'omed u'mishmua mipi ed v'ed mipi ed u'mipi adam ne'eman.
So right, lest you should, don't say something that's from an assumption
that you haven't seen the evidence literally with your own eyes or
from hearing from someone else or from hearing from someone who actually
did see the case with their own eyes or from someone who
you say, oh, they're actually a trustworthy person. שמא אי אתם יודעים
שסופנו לבדוק אתכם בדרישה ובחקירה. Shema ee atem yodim she'sofenu livdok etchem
b'drisha u'vchakira. Don't you know that we're going to end up testing
you with דרישה ובחקירה, drisha u'vchakira, asking them the specific questions where
were you, when were you in that place, all those things that
we learned about earlier. הוו יודעים שלא כדיני ממונות דיני נפשות. Havu
yodim shelo k'dinei mamonot dinei nefashot. Know that דיני ממונות dinei mamonot
and דיני נפשות dinei nefashot are not the same. דיני ממונות אדם
נותן ממון ומתכפר לו. Dinei mamonot adam noten mamon u'mitkaper lo. In
a situation of a, sorry, דיני ממונות, dinei mamonot, in a civil
case, right, where we're talking the difference between civil and capital cases,
in a civil case, someone could give money and then later be
atoned. What does that mean? That means that they could, let's say
someone was wrongfully had their money taken away from them, there's a
way to atone for that naturally by giving them back their money.
However, you're meaning even you the עדים, edim, you know, if you're
זוממין, zomemim, you can still like pay up. You can pay them
back. Right, exactly. דיני נפשות דמו ודם זרעיותיו תלוין בו עד סוף
העולם. Dinei nefashot damo v'dam zariotav tluyin bo ad sof ha'olam. In
the case where someone has been killed because of your testimony, his
blood and the blood of his descendants are kind of placed upon
you forever and ever. שכן מצינו. Sheken matzinu. And now we're going
to have this amazing, these amazing statements which a lot of you
have probably heard before, but I at least never knew were in
this context of threatening a witness, which makes them very interesting. שכן
מצינו בקין שהרג את אחיו שנאמר דמי אחיך צועקים. Sheken matzinu b'Kayin
she'harag et achiv shene'emar dmei achicha tzoakim. Like we see with קין
Kayin who killed his brother. It says the blood of your brother
cry out. Notice it says דמי, dmei, not דם, dam, the plural
there. Okay. So bloods. אינו אומר דם אחיך אלא דמי אחיך. Eino
omer dam achicha ela dmei achicha. There we go. It doesn't say
it's not in the singular, it doesn't say דם אחיך, dam achicha,
rather it says the plural, דמי אחיך. dmei achicha. דמו ודם זרעיותיו.
Damo v'dam zariotav. This implies both his blood and the blood of
all of his descendants. דבר אחר. Davar acher. Or perhaps why does
it say דמי אחיך? dmei achicha? שהיה דמו מושלך על העצים ועל
האבנים. Shehaya damo mushlach al ha'etzim v'al ha'avanim. And because the blood
of הבל Hevel was scattered upon all of the branches and stones.
So this is like a little מדרש, midrash, like a little aside
in the משנה. mishnah. They wouldn't say this part to עדים. edim.
Why don't they do this? יופי. Yofi. We're just saying דבר אחר.
davar acher. Oh, we're just saying now that part? I don't think
so. That's how I originally read it. I'll keep on going and
let me know if you still think that at the end. Okay?
If he like gets pushed off a cliff, he gets scatters on
the... Oh, oh, the דבר אחר devar acher you're saying is part
of the משנה. mishnah. Yeah, דבר אחר devar acher might not be,
but we're... oh I see, but we're going to go back and
it seems that what's after the דבר אחר devar acher at least,
it's still part of this same quote. Oh yeah, yeah that's the...
yeah not the דבר אחר. devar acher. Yeah, yeah, yeah. Okay, I
didn't understand. דבר אחר devar acher right, על העצים al ha-etzim right,
so the blood is scattered on the branches and the stones, meaning
in many different places. לפיכך Lefikach נברא אדם יחידי, nivra adam yechidi,
right? Therefore, man was created single, meaning there was אדם הראשון, Adam
HaRishon, the first man was created as one person, there weren't like
70 different people created at the same time or four different people
created at the same time, which is interesting because where is right
חוה Chavah and all of this obviously? But okay, we're going to
leave that aside for the moment. ללמדך שכל המאבד נפש אחת מישראל
מעלה עליו הכתוב כאילו איבד עולם מלא. lelamedcha she-kol ha-me'abed nefesh achat
mi-Yisrael ma'aleh alav ha-katuv ke'ilu ibed olam malei. Anyone who destroys a
single soul from Israel, the Torah treats him as though he has
destroyed an entire world. And this is super interesting because this word
מישראל mi-Yisrael wasn't there in all of the earliest printings. Okay? So
the original text seems to have said anyone who destroys a soul
and didn't specify whether it's a Jewish one or not. I wonder
why or when and in what context this word came in because
both הרמב"ם ha-Rambam and the old text of רש"י Rashi, and it
seems like all the old texts don't have that in. Okay. וכל
המקיים נפש אחת מישראל מעלה עליו הכתוב כאילו קיים עולם מלא. ve-chol
ha-mekayem nefesh achat mi-Yisrael ma'aleh alav ha-katuv ke'ilu kiyem olam malei. Okay,
but anyone who sustains a soul from Israel, it's as though the
Torah treats them as though they've sustained an entire world. ומפני שלום
הבריות, u-mipnei shalom ha-briyot, and also right, we're going to give all
these different reasons of why אדם Adam was created as a soul...
as only one person, or that rather humanity was created through one
ancestor. ומפני שלום הבריות, u-mipnei shalom ha-briyot, because of peace among peoples,
שלא יאמר אדם לחברו אבא גדול מאביך, shelo yomar adam le-chavero abba
gadol mei-avicha, my father is greater than your father. ושלא יהיו המינים
אומרים הרבה רשויות בשמים, ve-shelo yihyu ha-minim omrim harbeh rashuyot ba-shamayim, and
also because so that heretics wouldn't say that there are many powers
that be in the heaven. Right, like to say that basically, oh
you know Zeus created the first Greek and whatever, our God created
the first Jew, right, to avoid that kind of equation. ולהגיד גדולתו
של הקדוש ברוך הוא, u-lehagid gedulato shel HaKadosh Baruch Hu, and also
to tell the greatness of God. שאדם טובע כמה מטבעות בחותם אחד,
she-adam toveia kama matbe'ot be-chotam echad, because man he mints many coins
with the same mold, וכולם דומים זה לזה, ve-kulam domim zeh la-zeh,
and all of them end up looking the same. ומלך מלכי המלכים
הקדוש ברוך הוא, u-melech malchei ha-melachim HaKadosh Baruch Hu, but rather the
King of Kings, God, טבע כל אדם בחותמו של אדם הראשון, tava
kol adam be-chotamo shel Adam HaRishon, He stamps every individual with the
stamp of the first man, אדם הראשון, Adam HaRishon, ואין אחד מהן
דומה לחברו, ve-ein echad me-hen domeh le-chavero, and all humans end up
looking different. ולפיכך כל אחד ואחד חייב לומר, u-lefikach kol echad ve-echad
chayav lomar, therefore each and every individual is obligated to say, בשבילי
נברא העולם, bishvili nivra ha-olam, for my sake was the world created.
And if you look at the רש"י here, בשבילי נברא העולם, bishvili
nivra ha-olam, it's the very last line in the middle there of
the רש"י, בשבילי נברא העולם, bishvili nivra ha-olam, כלומר חשוב אני כעולם
מלא, klomar chashuv ani ke-olam malei, it's like saying that I am
considered like an entire world, לא אטרד את עצמי מן העולם בעבירה
אחת. lo etred et atzmi min ha-olam ba-aveira achat. Okay? Because if
you have that mindset you won't come to sin and then incur
upon yourselves the death penalties I think what we're talking about here.
So really it's you have a responsibility to sustain yourself and everyone
around you and make sure no one dies because an entire world
can come forth from you just like an entire world can come
forth from אדם. Adam. ושמא תאמרו, ve-shema tomru, okay, we're going on
to the next page now. שמא תאמרו מה לנו ולצרה הזאת. shema
tomru ma lanu u-la-tzara ha-zot. So now we're saying what happens if
the witness says, "מה לנו ולצרה הזאת? ma lanu u-la-tzara ha-zot? Why
should I put myself in this situation? Right, what is this to
me and connecting me and this horrible thing of destroying a person,
of killing, and having to kill someone?" Meaning now that they've scared
him. Exactly. Right. So I'm gonna go ahead out, right? I don't
want to be any part of this, this is terrifying. נו הלא
כבר נאמר, no halo kevar ne'emar, no there's a פסוק pasuk that
says, there's a verse that says, "והוא עד או ראה או ידע
אם לוא יגיד." ve-hu ed o ra'ah o yada im lo yagid.
Right, so there's a פסוק pasuk which says no, actually if you're
a witness and you see or you do something you need to
tell. Okay fine, so I need to be a witness but... But
I'm still worried, all right? What is this to me that I'm
gonna, I'm gonna be held responsible for the blood of this guilty
person, right? I give testimony and then it turns out they're guilty,
and now they've died, and all of these, you still told me
all of these terrible things, right? I'm gonna end up being held
guilty for all of these? No, הלא כבר נאמר halo kvar ne'emar
באבוד רשעים רינה. be'avod resha'im rina. Through the destruction of the wicked
there is rejoicing. So it's actually not going to be a bad
thing if someone who is guilty and you know they're guilty and
you give testimony and they end up dying, that's actually a good
thing. Okay, now let's go to the Gemara. תנו רבנן: tanu rabanan:
כיצד מאומד? keitzad me'umad? What is the situation that's from, we talked
about before in the Mishnah, a situation where you haven't seen the,
like, a super incredibly credible assumption? You haven't actually seen an act
being carried out, but it's super probable that it's happened. Okay, so
what's... sorry, what's מאומד? me'umad? How are you explaining that translation? I
think it's in the estimated... yeah, right, or assumption, or אומדנא umdana
is a term that the Gemara uses often, it's like using as
an assumption. So... אומר להם שמא כך ראיתם שרץ אחד אחר חבירו
לחורבה. omer lahem shema kach re'item sheratz echad achar chaveiro lechorba. Right?
So now we have a situation where you see, right, this is
what the witness would say to them, but wait, maybe I saw
someone running, I saw my fellow running into a ruin. ורצתם אחריו...
veratztem acharav... oh, okay, sorry, this is whatever, I got the speakers
flipped around. And you ran after him into the room. ומצאתם סייף
בידו ודמו מטפטף והרוג מפרפר umatzatem sa'if beyado u'damo metaptef veharug mefarper
and you saw a sword in his hand and blood dripping down
and you saw a dead body there in its death throes. אם
כך ראיתם לא ראיתם כלום. im kach re'item lo re'item klum. If
that's what you saw, that's not anything. That is no actual worth
in terms of testimony. Circumstantial evidence, right. Yeah. תניא אמר רבי שמעון
בן שטח. tanya amar rabbi Shimon ben Shatach. Okay, so now we're
gonna have a related statement by Rabbi Shimon ben Shatach. אראה בנחמה,
ereh benechama, אם לא ראיתי. im lo ra'iti. Okay, so this phrase
אראה בנחמה ereh benechama is a, seems to be an oath. It
comes up other times in the Gemara. It's super unclear what it
means exactly. There's all the ראשונים rishonim and whoever debate it, so
I don't know what it means. Like I'll see redemption if I
didn't see the case that אחד שרץ אחר חבירו לחורבה. echad sheratz
achar chaveiro lechorba. So I saw someone running into a ruin. ורצתי
אחריו וראיתי סייף בידו ודמו מטפטף והרוג מפרפר veratzti acharav vera'iti sa'if
beyado u'damo metaptef veharug mefarper and I saw a sword in his
hand and blood dripping down and a dead body convulsing. אמרתי לו
רשע, amarti lo rasha, I told him, wicked one! מי הרגו לזה,
mi harago lazeh, who killed this person? או אני או אתה, o
ani o ata, either me or you, and obviously it wasn't me,
right? אבל מה אעשה שאין דמך מסור בידי aval ma e'eseh she'ein
damcha masur beyadi because your blood is not in my hands, שהרי
אמרה תורה, sheharei amra torah, for after all the Torah said: על
פי שנים עדים יומת המת. al pi shnayim edim yumat hamet. According
to two witnesses the death sentence is carried out. So this is
really strange because weren't we talking about אומד, omed, right? We weren't
talking about the necessity of having two witnesses in order to carry
a case. We were talking about the necessity of having direct sight.
So this is also something that all of the ראשונים rishonim and
whoever talk about. And there's a תוספות tosfot which somehow coincides, but
basically says that there actually were other people with Rabbi Shimon ben
Shatach, it's just that the Gemara doesn't mention them. And so there
were two witnesses in order to see it, or rather in order
to have this אומד, omed, not see it directly. And Rabbi Shimon
ben Shatach is also learning the laws of direct sight, right, not
relying on אומד omed from the same פסוק pasuk as the necessity
of having two witnesses. So it's a little far-fetched, but that shows
you how strange it is that in the Gemara it doesn't really
line up exactly. Okay. היודע מחשבות יפרע מאותו איש. hayodea machshavot yipara
me'oto ish. The one who knows thoughts will punish this man, i.e.,
God will punish him, שהרג את חבירו, sheharag et chaveiro, for killing
his fellow. אמרו לא זזו משם עד שבא נחש והכישו. amru lo
zazu misham ad sheba nachash vehikisho. So at that very moment, a
snake came and bit the person with the sword in hand. And
they died. Okay. והאי בר נחש הוא? Veha'i bar nachash hu? But
wait a second, was he liable for death by snake? והאמר רב
יוסף, Veha'amar Rav Yosef, didn't Rav Yosef say? וכן תני דבי חזקיה,
Vechen tani debei Chizkiyya, and so too was taught in the house
of Chizkiyya: מיום שחרב בית המקדש, Miyom shecharav Beit HaMikdash, אף על
פי שבטלה סנהדרין, af al pi shebatla Sanhedrin, ארבע מיתות לא בטלו.
arba mitot lo batlu. So from the day that the the Temple
was destroyed, even though that the Sanhedrin was nullified, the penalties for
the four death sentence penalties were not annulled. Okay. לא בטלו? והא
בטלו! Lo batlu? Veha batlu! What do you mean they weren't annulled?
They were annulled! We know that, right? That's a fact. אלא דין
ארבע מיתות לא בטלו. Ela din arba mitot lo batlu. No, no,
no, you misunderstood. It's true that the formal earthly process for carrying
out the death penalty, these four death penalties, are no longer around,
but nevertheless God carries them out, right? הדין, Hadin, the judgment, thank
you, still existed in the world, it just wasn't by human. Okay,
there's an interesting תוספות Tosafot here, which is like the two, four,
six, eight, maybe tenth line, ואי תימא ve'in tema at the end
of the line. It starts with מיום שחרב בית המקדש. Miyom shecharav
Beit HaMikdash. ואי תימא, Ve'in tema, והא קאתי הוו מיתי למינכת מ'
שנה קודם חורבן הבית? veha kati havu maiti lemincat mem shana kodem
churban habayit? But wait a second, there was the Sanhedrin was stopped
being functional forty years before the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash was destroyed,
right? So why doesn't the Gemara say, oh, from forty years before
the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash was destroyed? Okay, good question. כדאמר בפרק
היו בודקין, Kedamar beperek hayu bodkin, as we know from פרק היו
בודקין, Perek Hayu Bodkin, שגלתה סנהדרין וישבה לה בחנות, shegalta Sanhedrin veyashva
lah bechanut, ואמר שלא דנו דיני נפשות, ve'amar shelo danu dinei nefashot,
because we know that forty years before, the Sanhedrin which, if you
look in that סוגיא sugya it'll show there, that the Sanhedrin was
what's it called, exiled, and sat in חנות, Chanut, in absentia, didn't
function. ואמר שלא דנו דיני נפשות, Ve'amar shelo danu dinei nefashot, oh,
and right, ויש לומר מכל מקום שהיו ראויים לצורך שעה, veyesh lomar
mikol makom shehayu re'uyim letzorech sha'ah, so it's true that it wasn't
regularly functioning, but in special cases they would come and convene, היו
חוזרים ללשכת הגזית hayu chozrim lelishkat hagazit and they would come and
convene in the לשכת הגזית, Lishkat HaGazit, which is in the temple.
ההוא עובדא וכיוצא בו, Hahu uvda vekayotze bo, like that one case
and others. So what's that one case? This is actually a situation
of censorship, and as you might know, a lot of times in
the גמרא, Gemara, there's places where the original text has been censored,
either by Christian censors or by Jews who don't want to make
Christians angry in the Middle Ages, we're talking about. And so if
you look at שטיינזלץ Steinsaltz, I think has the original text, and
if you look at עוז והדר, the edition has it in the
footnotes. It says ההוא עובדא דישו, hahu uvda deYeshu, the case of
Jesus. So that's interesting, was there a and that was then taken
out because they didn't want to have Christians come across that text
I guess. But it's also interesting, like is this a is there
also a Jewish tradition of Jesus being tried by the Sanhedrin, or
is this just taken from Christian texts and understood to be the
case? I don't know, but interesting to know. Where were we reading
from? The תוספות. Tosafot. Yeah. Okay, now going back to the גמרא,
okay, so we're talking about the four death penalties still being carried
out by God even though not through formal legal process. מי שנתחייב
סקילה, Mi shenitchayev sekilah, so someone who was deserved punishment by stoning,
או נופל מן הגג, o nofel min hagag, so it ends up
that you would fall off from a roof, because we know stoning
involves pushing someone off from a cliff, או חיה דורסתו, o chayah
doresato, or a wild animal would kill them, tear them up. מי
שנתחייב שריפה, Mi shenitchayev sereifah, someone who deserves death by burning, או
נופל בדליקה, o nofel bidleikah, they would end up dying in a
fire, או נחש מכישו, o nachash mekisho, or a snake would bite
them, okay, which was our case, right? If you remember. מי שנתחייב
הריגה, Mi shenitchayev harigah, someone who is death by sword, או נמסר
למלכות, o nimsar lammalchut, he would end up being the death sentence
would be carried out by the non-Jewish authorities, או ליסטים באים עליו,
o listim ba'im alav, or bandits would come upon him and kill
him. מי שנתחייב חנק, Mi shenitchayev chenek, someone who is deserved of
strangulation, או שטובע בנהר, o shetoveia bannahar, either he would drown in
the river, או מת בסרונכי, o met bisserunchi, or he would die
of serunchi, which is I don't know, some sort of disease. אמרי
ההוא חטא אחריני הוה ביה *amrei hahu chata acharini havah beih*. Oh,
ההוא חטא אחריני *hahu chata acharini*, but wait a second. Our guy
in the case died by snake and we know from other source
things that someone who is a murderer, their fitting punishment is death
by sword. So what's going on? ההוא חטא אחריני הוה ביה *hahu
chata acharini havah beih*. Oh, sorry. Okay, so that's all the background.
אמרי ההוא חטא אחריני הוה ביה *amrei hahu chata acharini havah beih*.
No, no, no, what actually happened was that he had another sin
that he did that deserved the death penalty by שריפה *sreifah*, fire,
right? He committed a murder and he did something else which made
him liable for death by שריפה *sreifah*, fire. Oh, I'm just what's
it called translating שריפה *sreifah* as fire. In סנהדרין Sanhedrin *Sanhedrin* it's
not actually, it's like burning boiling metal down your throat but okay,
yeah, just to clarify. So they're saying he had something else coming?
Correct, he exactly, he had something else coming to him, right, he
wasn't right. דאמר מר מי שנתחייב שתי מיתות בית דין נידון בחמורה
*de'amar mar mi shenitchayev shtei mitot bet din nidon bachalmurah*, someone who
is liable for two different death penalties is judged by the more
serious case, which is שריפה *sreifah* is a more serious case than
הריגה *harigah*, than sword. Okay, מאומד *me'omet*. ובדיני נפשות הוא דלא אמרינן
הא בדיני ממונות אמרינן *uvdinei nefashot hu delo amrinan ha bedinei mamonot
amrinan*. So if we go back to the משנה *Mishnah*, it says
that in a situation of capital cases we do not use an
אומדנא *umdana*, we do not use an assumption that something happened even
when we didn't actually see it, we just saw all the surrounding
circumstances. That implies that in civil cases we do use this אומדנא
*umdana*, this assumption. כמאן *keman*? Whose opinion is that like? כרבי אחא
*keRabbi Acha*. That's like כרבי אחא *keRabbi Acha*. דתניא רבי אחא אומר
גמל האוחז בין הגמלים ונמצא גמל הרוג בצדו וידוע שזה הרגו *detanya
Rabbi Acha omer gamal ha'ochez bein hagamalim venimtza gamal harug betzido viyadu'a
shezeh harago*. So רבי אחא *Rabbi Acha* says if there's a situation
where there's a camel האוחז *ha'ochez*, that's it's a very strange word,
maybe it means in heat, maybe it means some angry, I don't
know, it's unclear, רש"י *Rashi* himself brings a couple of opinions. So
you have this feisty camel for whatever reason amongst the other camels
and you end up you know that this camel is not a
happy camel or is too happy perhaps, and you end up finding
a dead camel right next to them. וידוע שזה הרגו *viyadu'a shezeh
harago*, it's obvious that this one camel killed the other camel. Okay,
so that shows he does hold by the idea of an אומדנא
*umdana*, of an assumption. ולטעמיך *uletameich*? But now the editor of the
גמרא *Gemara* says but if you're holding the fact that because something
happened in a capital doesn't work in a capital case it does
work in a civil case, you would have to do that for
all of the things listed in the משנה *Mishnah*. ולטעמיך *uletameich*, if
that's the case, עד מפי עד דקתני בדיני נפשות הוא דלא אמרינן
הא בדיני ממונות אמרינן *ed mipi ed degatani bidinei nefashot hu delo
amrinan ha bedinei mamonot amrinan*. But if that's the case, we said
that you can't use a second-hand testimony in a capital case. So
therefore would that imply that you can use second-hand testimony in a
civil case? That's bizarre. והתנן *vehatnan*, because after all, isn't it taught:
אם אמר הוא אמר לי שאני חייב לו איש פלוני אמר לי
שהוא חייב לו לא אמר כלום עד שיאמר בפנינו הודה לו שהוא
חייב לו מאתים זוז *im amar hu amar li she'ani chayav lo
ish ploni amar li shehu chayav lo lo amar klum ad sheyomar
befanenu hodah lo shehu chayav lo matayim zuz*. Right, so we know
from other places that if someone tells you that they're owed money
by someone else then that's not valid testimony until they admit before
you with an oath that someone else is obligated them a specific
amount of money, right, that's also before two witnesses רש"י *Rashi* brings
in. אלמא אף על גב דפסילי בדיני ממונות אמרינן להו בדיני נפשות
הכא נמי אף על גב דפסילי בדיני ממונות אמרינן להו בדיני נפשות
*alma af al gav depsilei bidinei mamonot amrinan lehu bidinei nefashot hacha
nami af al gav depsilei bidinei mamonot amrinan lehu bidinei nefashot*. Right,
so if that's the case that we know that even though it's
invalid we know that עד מפי עד *ed mipi ed*, second-hand testimony
is invalid in the case of civil courts and it's also invalid
in the case of capital courts. We don't learn this assumption because
it's not good in capital courts it is good in civil courts.
So too with our first situation, even though we don't have direct
proof, we're going to learn by analogy that with an אומדנא, with
an assumption, just because we explicitly know that it's not good in
a capital court case that does not mean that it is good
in a civil case, right? You can't do that in any situation.
That's basically the gist of it. Okay. הבו ידים, Habu yadim, this
is going back to the דמי, damei, the multiple... plural of blood,
the word blood that we were learning out before. אמר רב יהודה
בריה דרב חייא, Amar Rav Yehuda brei de-Rav Hiya, רב יהודה Rav
Yehuda the son of רב חייא, Rav Hiya, מלמד שעשה קין בהבל
אחיו חבורות חבורות פצעות פצעות. melamed she-asa Kayin be-Hevel achiv chaburot chaburot
petza'ot petza'ot. So he would teach that קין Kayin made many different
bruises and injuries on his brother שלא היה יודע מהיכן נשמה יוצאת
she-lo haya yodea me-heichan neshama yotzei because he didn't know where the
soul departs עד שהגיע לצאורו ad she-higi'a le-tzavaro until he reached his
neck and learned that that's how you in fact kill someone. אמר
רב יהודה בריה דרב חייא, Amar Rav Yehuda brei de-Rav Hiya, מיום
שפתחה הארץ. mi-yom she-patcha ha-aretz. Now we just have another statement of
רב יהודה בריה דרב חייא. Rav Yehuda brei de-Rav Hiya. He says
from the day that the earth opened up פתחה הארץ את פיה,
patcha ha-aretz et piha, its mouth, וקיבלה את דמו של הבל, ve-kibla
et damo shel Hevel, and opened up its mouth and received the
blood of הבל, Hevel, שוב לא פתחה, shuv lo patcha, it no
longer opened up its mouth, שנאמר מכנף הארץ זמירות שמענו צבי לצדיק.
shene'emar mi-kenaf ha-aretz zemirot shama'nu tzevi la-tzaddik. From the edges of the
earth we heard song saying glory to the righteous, right? So it's
not from... מכנף הארץ ולא מפי הארץ. mi-kenaf ha-aretz ve-lo mi-pi ha-aretz.
So there the fact that it says from the edges of the
earth and not the mouth of the earth shows that it no
longer opened up its mouth. Oh, I don't think I have time
but there's an interesting תוספות Tosafot here too talking about the קדושה
Kedusha and how they would only say it on שבת Shabbos in
ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. Okay. איתיביה חזקיה אחיו, Etivei Hiskiya achiv, his
brother חזקיה Hiskiya brought a contradictory proof. Here it's a verse: ותפתח
הארץ את פיה. va-tiftach ha-aretz et piha. But wait a second, we
know from קרח Korach that the earth did open up its mouth,
right? It says and the land opened up its mouth. Yes. Oh,
that's interesting, right? That's cool. אמר ליה לרעה פתחה לטובה לא פתחה.
Amar lei le-ra'a patcha le-tova lo patcha. No, no, no, that was
opening up its mouth to accept an evil person, not to accept
a good person. אמר רב יהודה בריה דרב חייא, Amar Rav Yehuda
brei de-Rav Hiya, so רב יהודה Rav Yehuda the son of רב
חייא Rav Hiya says גלות מכפר עוון מחצה galut mechaper avon mechtza
that exile atones for half of the sin. מעיקרא, Me-ikara, originally כתיב
ketiv it's written והייתי נע ונד. ve-hayiti na va-nad. Originally it says
in the context of קין, Kayin, I was both נע na and
ונד. va-nad. ולבסוף U-le-vasof כתיב ketiv and after that it was written
וישב בארץ נוד. va-yeshev be-eretz Nod. And he settled in the land
of נוד. Nod. נוד Nod being connected with נע, na, right? So
there's still a נוד Nod involved but there's no נע ונד. na
va-nad. נע ונד na va-nad literally means a wanderer, right? Like a
moves and moves or whatever. Right. But now there's only... Correct. Not
two. Exactly. Right. There's only half of it. That's the point, right?
The other half was atoned for ostensibly. אמר רב יהודה גלות מכפר
שלושה דברים. Amar Rav Yehuda galut mechaper shelosha devarim. Now we're arguing
about what is it that... how much does exile actually atone. It
atones for three things says רב יהודה, Rav Yehuda, שנאמר היושב בעיר
הזאת ימות בחרב וברעב ובדבר. shene'emar ha-yoshev ba-ir ha-zot yamut ba-cherev u-va-ra'av
u-va-dever. And he who dwells in this city will die through sword,
through starvation and through pestilence. והיוצא ונפל על הכשדים, ve-ha-yotzei ve-nafal al
ha-kasdim, and he who exits and falls into the hands of the
כשדים Kasdim הצרים, ha-tzarim, the besieging כשדים, Kasdim, these people who were
besieging the town at that point, עליכם יחיה והיתה לו נפשו לשלל.
aleichem yichye ve-hayeta lo nafsho le-shalal. So among them he will live
and his soul or whatever he will end up being like loot
for them. Right? So that shows that if you're being exiled into
the lands of the כשדים, Kasdim, you no longer... you will be
atoned for the punishments that would end up giving you these three
things. You're still going to be alive. You're going to be alive.
You're not going to be dead by sword, by famine, or by
pestilence. Okay. Is רב יהודה Rav Yehuda the son of חייא Hiya
the same... Sorry, what was it? First it says רב יהודה... Rav
Yehuda... רב יהודה, Rav Yehuda, no, those are two different people. Oh,
I see, that's the two different people. Correct. Those are different people.
רבי יוחנן אמר Rabbi Yochanan amar גלות מכפרת על הכל. galut mechaperet
al hakol. רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says exile atones for everything, שנאמר
shene'emar כתבו את האיש הזה ערירי גבר לא יצלח בימיו כי לא
יצלח מזרעו איש ישב על כסא דוד ומשל עוד ביהודה. kitvu et
ha'ish hazeh ariri gever lo yitzlach beyamav ki lo yitzlach mizar'o ish
yoshev al kisse David umoshel od biYehuda. Okay, it says write this
man as if he should be write off this man that he
should be childless. He is talking about יכניה Yechonya in the very
last days of the first temple, that he should be childless, shouldn't
no one he shouldn't be successful in his days and his all
of his descendants won't be successful to sit on the the throne
of David and to rule in the land of יהודה Yehuda anymore.
So basically all he won't have any his children will not end
up ruling and they he won't have any children they won't end
up ruling. Okay. His line will be cut off. ובתר דגלה, Uvatar
degala, but afterwards that he was exiled, כתיב ketiv ובני יכניה uvnei
Yechanya אסיר שאלתיאל בנו. Assir She'altiel beno. He has children, right? So
the fact that he was exiled atoned for whatever his punishment that
wouldn't give him children and now he has children. Okay. Why is
he called אסיר? Assir? שעיברתו אמו בבית האסורים she'ibarto imo bevet ha'asurim
because his mother conceived in jail. אסירין asirin אסיר. Assir. Okay. There
is a comment here you know that יכניה Yechonya had two sons
and then as it says his son זרובבל Zerubbabel who will lead
the exiles when they came back to Israel and built the second.
Oh great. So maybe it is not even just that, right, that
he had children but it is that they ended up being like
a real thing. Thank you. That is very helpful. Coming up onto
the next page, right, it gives a preview of tomorrow, but that
is alright. Okay. שאלתיאל She'altiel ששתלו אל שלא כדרך הנטעים. sheshatlo el
shelo kederech haneta'im. ששתלו אל? Sheshatlo El? No. ששתלו. Sheshatlo. Yeah, correct.
ששתלו אל שלא כדרך הנטעים. Sheshatlo El shelo kederech haneta'im. He was
called שאלתיאל She'altiel because he wasn't planted in the normal way of
plantings. גמירי שאין אשה מתעברת מעומד gemiri she'ein isha mit'aberet me'umad because
a woman normally does not conceive while standing. The idea is jail
is a very, there's not a lot of space in jail. They
were standing? Yeah, according to רש״י, Rashi, yes. Okay and just two
more lines just to finish. דבר אחר davar acher שאלתיאל She'altiel שנשאל
על אלתו אל shenish'al al alato el because God freed his oath,
no longer absolved his oath. זרובבל Zerubbabel שנזרע בבבל. shenizra beVavel. Why
is he called זרובבל? Zerubbabel? Because he was seeded in בבל. Bavel.
ומה שמו Uma shemo נחמיה בן חכליה שמו. Nechemia ben Chachalya shemo.
And what was his name? I think we're talking about זרובבל Zerubbabel
right, which is it's actually it's a good question the מרגליות Margoliyot
there is a commentary who is confused because it seems like they
are not the same person but here we're saying they are the
same person, so his name was נחמיה Nechemia was נחמיה בן חכליה.
Nechemia ben Chachalya. And thus ends סנהדרין thirty-seven. Okay, how do I
turn this off?